Register of the World War I subject collection
Hoover Institution Archives
World War I subject collection
1882-2015
1914-1919
XX739
Hoover Institution Archives
30 manuscript boxes, 14 oversize boxes, 19 oversize folders, 1 microfilm reel (35.8 linear feet)
Books, booklets, correspondence, drawings, flyers, forms, leaflets, maps, memorabilia, newspapers and clippings, pamphlets, press releases, sheet music, and other printed matter and ephemera relating to military operations and home front conditions, particularly in Germany and the United States, during World War I.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Contents of Collection
This collection consists of a wide assortment of materials relating to World War I, and, to a lesser extent, the period immediately before and after, acquired from and donated by various individuals over time. As a result, in certain instances there are groupings of materials on the same topic, although often there are other materials on the same topic located elsewhere in the collection.
One major topic of the collection is military operations, including recruiting and enlistment; orders and instructions; battle summaries and war news, particularly related to battle lines and fronts (often in the form of maps); and occupation of enemy territory. While there is some material related to the British and French militaries, as well as those of other European countries involved in the war, the bulk of the materials on this topic relate to the German and United States militaries. The American materials are largely about recruiting and enlistment, while the German materials feature war news, military orders, and notices to inhabitants of occupied towns.
Another major topic of the collection is home front conditions, including financing the war, garnering public support for the war, patriotic activities, and rationing. The United War Work Campaign and Liberty bonds in the United States and Kriegsanleihe (war bonds) in Germany are particularly well represented. Also of note are drawings and cartoons, which often depict caricatures of the nations involved in the war, as well as sheet music of patriotic songs, largely from the United States and France. Additionally, there are ration cards from Germany, Great Britain, France, Russia, and Poland and informational materials from the United States about the rationing of food and goods.
The collection also covers the German Revolution of 1918 and the work of welfare/relief organizations such as the Red Cross, Y.M.C.A., American Committee for Relief in the Near East, and others.
Types of materials found on these topics include: books, booklets, correspondence, flyers, forms, leaflets, memorabilia, pamphlets, press releases, and other printed matter and ephemera. Also included in the collection are contemporaneous newspapers and clippings, again predominantly from Germany and the United States, relating news of the war.
World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Germany.; Germany--History--Revolution, 1918.
- Clippings, Les Annales politiques et littéraires, circa 1914-1919 (Box-folder 1: 1-6)
- Clippings, Les Annales politiques et littéraires, circa 1914-1919 (Box-folder 2: 1-3)
- Newspaper clippings, German newspapers, 1914 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  Scope and Contents note
  In German.
- Newspaper clippings, war news, circa 1915-1919 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  Compiled by George F. Tyler. A couple articles are in French.
- Newspaper clippings, sinking of the Lusitania and service letters, 1918, 1961, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  Three clippings. One, undated, is titled "Berlin Ordered Sinking of Lusitania; Proof of Germany's Crime in Code Cypher." The second, dated April 30, 1961, is titled "American Heritage--Fate Placed Lusitania, U20 in Same Part of Atlantic--And Sent US to War." The third, dated April 20, 1918, consists of service letters written by Paul Galloway, of the 116th field hospital with the American expeditionary forces, to his parents and a brother.
- Certificate for the Lübeckische Hanseatenkreuz [medal], 1918 June 5 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  Given by "der Senat der freien und Hansestadt Lübeck." Includes a handwritten section with the name of the recipient, which is not completely legible. In German.
- Letter from German prisoner-of-war to his family, 1918 February 27 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Booklet, "Première Lettre adressée aux Prisonniers Français,", 1914 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  Includes handwritten annotations and corrections.
- Drawing, "My Country, 'Tis of Thee,", 1916 February 10 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  Reprint of a satirical drawing from Life, distributed by The American Rights Committee, imagining what a map of North America would look like if the United States lost the war (e.g., New Prussia, Japonica, Turconia).
- Essays for Americans by Florizel von Reuter, undated (Box-folder 2: 11)
  Three essays intended for American audiences written by Florizel von Reuter, an American living in Germany and a correspondent on the staff of the Neutral Committee for Neutral Reports, Berlin. The essays, which are pro-Germany, are titled, "The Attitude of the United States. Is America Neutral?," "Was Belgium's Attitude Towards Germany Justified?," and "More Triple Entente Fables About German Atrocities."
- Leaflet, "An die Berliner Bevölkerung,", undated (Box-folder 2: 12)
  Pro-German leaflet asserting Germany's desire for peace.
- Leaflet, "The Breach of Belgian Neutrality by England and Belgium,", undated (Box-folder 2: 13)
  Pro-German leaflet asserting that prior to the outbreak of the war "Belgium was conniving with the Entente Powers."
- Leaflet, "Deceiving the Whole World. American Newspaper Men Arrested in London for Telling the Truth about Germany. -- A Personal Letter,", 1914 October 6 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  From the Chicago Tribune, by James O'Donnell Bennett: a personal letter to the editor about his experience in Germany.
- Leaflet, "England's perfidy exposed by Americans,", 1914 October 12 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  Pro-German declaration by the Committee of The American Truth Society in Munich concluding that England is directly responsible for the war.
- Leaflet, "Der gegenwärtige krieg ist das Werk Deutschlands,", undated (Box-folder 2: 16)
- Leaflet, "The German People Offers [sic] Peace,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  In English and French.
- Leaflet, open letter by Professor Leon Rains, 1914 September (Box-folder 3: 2)
  Pro-German, open letter written by Professor Leon Rains, in Dresden, relating a Red Cross officer's tale of supposed Belgian and French atrocities.
- Leaflet, "La paix en vue!,", 1918 September 22 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  From on the Verdun Front.
- Leaflet, "To the People and Press of America,", 1914 October 13 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  Pro-German, open letter written by Katherine Thayer Hobson-Kraus, refuting tales of "German Vandalism."
- Leaflet, "Sehr geehrter Herr?,", 1914 December (Box-folder 3: 5)
  From the Deutscher Überseedienst (German Overseas Service).
- Leaflet, "Wer zählt sie alle…,", undated (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Leaflet, "Who broke the Peace of Europe?,", circa 1914 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  Pro-German, asserts that the Triple Entente had been planning a war against Germany well before war broke out.
- Typescript, "Fliegerabwurfschriften als Propagandamittel während des Weltkrieges 1914-1918,", undated (Box-folder 3: 8)
  Brief analysis of German leaflet propaganda during World War I.
- Zettel, Bilder und Zeitschriftenfolgen, Subject File, 1914-1918 (Box-folder 3: 9-15)
  These items were gathered together by a donor. According to a type-written note at the front, they are various printed materials that were dropped by Allied planes over German lines, mostly demanding an end to the war. They were not in a discernible order, so they have been arranged by document type, with a few exceptions (one, where there were many instances of a single publication and two, when the items were in languages other than German). Where possible, the items were removed from the construction paper they were on. Some of the items are annotated/described by the compiler of the album. In German, unless otherwise noted.
  - Booklets (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Leaflets (Box-folder 3: 10-11)
  - Maps (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Newsletters and newspapers (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - "By Balloon/Durch Luftballon" (Box-folder 3: 14)
    These items all have "By Balloon/Durch Luftballon" printed on them, and they are numbered as well, suggesting that they are part of a series of a publication.
  - Other languages (Box-folder 3: 15)
    Includes items in French, Polish, and Russian.
- Booklet, "Euch Helden sei Dank!,", 1917 (Box-folder 3: 16)
- Booklet, "Heb mich auf!,", 1918 (Box-folder 3: 17)
- Booklet, "Prisonniers de Guerre,", 1918 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  Reproductions of drawings by Jean-Pierre Laurens.
- Drawings, "Aus einem Tage-Buch 1914," Erste Mappe, 1915 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  Reproductions of drawings by Adolf Hengeler that were distributed in Germany. Bild 1-6.
- Drawings, "Aus einem Tage-Buch 1914," Zweite Mappe, 1915 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  Reproductions of drawings by Adolf Hengeler that were distributed in Germany. Bild 7-12.
- Drawings, "Aus einem Tage-Buch 1914," Dritte Mappe, 1915 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  Reproductions of drawings by Adolf Hengeler that were distributed in Germany. Bild 13-18.
- Drawings, "Aus einem Tage-Buch 1914," Vierte Mappe, 1915 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  Reproductions of drawings by Adolf Hengeler that were distributed in Germany. Bild 19-24.
- Drawings, "Aus einem Tage-Buch 1914," Fünfte Mappe, 1915 (Box-folder 3: 23)
  Reproductions of drawings by Adolf Hengeler that were distributed in Germany. Bild 25-30.
- Drawings, "Aus einem Tage-Buch 1914/15," Sechste Mappe, 1915 (Box-folder 3: 24)
  Reproductions of drawings by Adolf Hengeler that were distributed in Germany. Bild 31-36.
- Drawings, "Aus einem Tage-Buch 1915," Siebente Mappe, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 25)
  Reproductions of drawings by Adolf Hengeler that were distributed in Germany. Bild 37-42.
- Flyer, "An das deutsche Volk! … Wollt Ihr noch einmal Weihnachten im Kriege feiern?,", undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Flyer, "Deutsche Soldaten! Rumänien, welches mit den Zentralmächten verbündet war…,", undated (Box-folder 4: 2)
- Flyer, "Ein paar vernünftige Worte an meine ehemaligen Kameraden,", 1916 February 9 (Box-folder 4: 3)
- Flyer, "Polacy! Wybiła godzina, kiedy marzenia Waszych ojców i dziadów mogą spełnić się…,", 1914 August 14 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  Call to the Polish people to welcome and join with Russia. In Polish and Russian.
- Leaflet, "An die süddeutschen!,", undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
- Leaflet, "Auf zum Endkampf!,", undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
- Leaflet, "Briefe aus Deutschland,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 7)
- Leaflet, "Deutsches Volk! Du erlebst ein neues Verdun…,", undated (Box-folder 4: 8)
- Leaflet, "Republik bedeutet Friede und Freiheit!,", undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
- Leaflet, "Wer hat die Kriegsfackel entzündet?,", 1916 December 17 (Box-folder 4: 10)
- Photographs, General Luigi Cadorna, 1916, undated (Box-folder 4: 11)
  Two photographs, one of Cadorna at his desk, and one of him as a young man (possibly during his time at the Turin Military Academy).
- Tables, "Losses in Men and Ships Suffered by Italy During the War,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  Five tables: 1) Losses suffered by the Italian army and navy from 23 May 1915 to 11 November 1918; 2) Casualties in officers and men; 3) Summary of the disabled from war causes; 4) Losses in the Royal Navy; 5) Italian merchant ships sunk by submarines and mines.
- 32 Textes du President Wilson, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  Cards of "memorable utterances of President Wilson" illustrated by Gustave Jacobs for the students of France (in French). Also included is a letter, stamped 21 February 1919, from the Minister of Public Education in France informing the educational authorities in the United States about the creation of the cards and enclosing a set.
- British, French, and American materials re monetary support of the war, undated (Box-folder 4: 14)
  Includes a British leaflet about saving money; French leaflets dropped from airplanes about the 3rd Defense Loan; an American Victory Bonds pin, and Worcester War Chest tags. In English and French.
- Declarations of British authors, 1914, undated (Box-folder 4: 15)
  Two leaflets: one, titled "To our colleagues in Russia," which discusses the inspiration the authors have drawn from Russian literature and Russia as a worthy ally in the war; the other, titled "The War: Declaration by British Authors," expressing their opinion that Great Britain was right to enter the war and their support for the Allies' cause.
- Excerpt from report about the British National Committee of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 16)
- Excerpt from report about establishment of foyers in Bourges, undated (Box-folder 4: 17)
- French iconography, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  Appears to be the cover of a book or album. Features the phrase "Nous combattons pour la liberté des peuples" over symbols of war/France and the words "République Française, 1914-1917."
- Matthias, Blanche C. materials, 1916-1919, 1925, 1983 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  Correspondence (1918-1919), publications ("Le Problème des Nationalités," by Th. Ruyssen, 1916 and "The Secret History of a Great Betrayal, Sixth Edition," by E.D. Morel, 1925), and a photocopy of Matthias' obituary, 1983.
- Miscellany, undated (Box-folder 4: 20)
  One Franc; stickers to fasten posters that say "Armenia: The most tragic story in human history;" wallet-sized fold-out "Flags of the Allies;" Camps Library bookmarks about donating books or magazines; Smileage Books of coupons for military entertainment venues; Worcester, MA employee identification cards; blank participation cards related to "l'Oeuvre;" notice from the 84th U.S. Infantry "Railsplitter" Division to German soldiers urging them to surrender; roster of German officers with rank and date of death (if applicable).
- Publisher/publications materials, undated (Box-folder 4: 21)
  The majority of the items are from the publisher/printer Coquemer and include, among other things, a notice about a reproduction of the painting "L'Aube de la Revanche;" "Elle Tiendra" leaflet; informational leaflets; a book jacket, and a notice about the publication of a patriotic calendar for 1918.
- Blank stationery/cards/postcards, undated (Box-folder 4: 22)
  Includes two sets of War Designs postcards illustrated by Frank Brangwyn, as well as a set of U.S. Marines postcards. Most of the items are in French.
- Booklet, The Barb Magazine, Vol. 1, No. 1, 1918 October (Box-folder 4: 23)
- Booklet, "Le Danger pour l'Église est en Allemagne,", 1915 (Box-folder 4: 24)
- Booklet, "The Great War,", 1914 September (Box-folder 4: 25)
  Speech delivered by the Right Honorable David Lloyd George, M.P. (Chancellor of the Exchequer) at the Queen's Hall, London, on 19 September 1914.
- Booklet, "La Marne,", 1917 (Box-folder 4: 26)
  "La Marne" is a poem by Robert de Bédarieux, dated 8 September 1916. Heading on the cover of the booklet, as well as on each page, reads "Les voix humaines: le blé rouge."
- Booklet, "Report of General John J. Pershing, U.S.A.,", 1919 (Box-folder 4: 27)
  Text of a cable from Pershing, Commander-in-Chief of the American Expeditionary Forces, to the Secretary of War, 20 November 1918. The cover notes that it was corrected 16 January 1919. The maps meant to accompany the report can be found in the Map case, Folder 1, Items 4 and 5.
- Booklet, "Strophes Patriotiques, " 2e Fascicule, undated (Box-folder 4: 28)
- Calendars, 1917, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 29)
  The 1917 pocket-sized calendar, in Italian, is published by the Banca Italiana di Sconto. The 1919 wallet-sized calendars, in French, feature photographs or drawings and quotations relating to the war.
- Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 4: 30)
  Includes a notice from Marshall Foch about the ceasing of hostilities on 11 November 1918; a letter dated 30 November 1918 from William Joseph Shipsey about his experience fighting in the war; correspondence from August 1917 about a false French publisher who went by the name Delandre; and a postcard dated 1 March 1919. In English and French.
- Drawings, "Tales of Three Nations,", circa 1923 (Box-folder 4: 31)
  Nine cartoons by Max Beerbohm, reproduced in the Manchester Guardian Weekly, depicting the relationship between England, France, and Germany from the early years of the nineteenth century through January 1923.
- Flyer, "Attaques par Gaz,", undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
- Flyer, "Civilians of Brussels Victims to German Artillery Fire,", circa 1916 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  There is a second copy of the flyer, in French.
- Flyer, "Die Sklaverei des deutschen Volkes,", undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
- Flyer, "Warum heimgekehrte Kriegsgefangene den Mund halten müssen,", undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
- Illustration, Décorations de Guerre: France, Belgique; Serbie, Montenegro, Roumanie; de l'Empire Britannique; Italie, Russie, Japon, undated (Box-folder 5: 5)
  Four posters with illustrations and names of the different medals awarded by various countries. In French.
- Leaflet, "Die amerikanischen Truppen rücken mit Eile heran,", undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
- Leaflet, "The Beacon,", undated (Box-folder 5: 7)
  Leaflets Nos. 1 ("British war aims"), 3 ("War for ever"), 4 ("'Necessity knows no Law'") and 6 ("Krupp's director on German policy").
- Leaflet, "The British Navy's Part,", 1918 August (Box-folder 5: 8)
  Text of a speech by Prime Minister Lloyd George in the House of Commons, 7 August 1918.
- Leaflet, "The Collapse of German Credit,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 5: 9)
- Leaflet, "Friedenshindernisse,", circa 1919 (Box-folder 5: 10)
- Leaflet, "Die geheim-presse im besetzten Belgien 1914/18,", 1920 (Box-folder 5: 11)
- Leaflet, "German War Ethics,", 1915 May 8 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  Article reprinted from The Tablet, A Weekly Newspaper and Review.
- Leaflet, "La Lettre du Soldat à Ceux du Pays Envahi,", 1917 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  Nos. 10 and 11.
- Leaflet, "Official Greeting to the Soldiers, Sailors and Marines at the Great Peace Jubilee,", 1919 October (Box-folder 5: 14)
  From a celebration of Fraternal Victory Day in Philadelphia, PA, 11 October 1919, by Edward Newton Haag, LL.B.
- Leaflet, "The performances of the association 'Karitas' [in] the year 1920,", circa 1920 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  Summary of a report of the association's activity, which consisted of providing aid to children and the poor in Europe.
- Leaflet, "Town of Lokeren,", 1914 October 24 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  Translation of order from German Kommandantur at Lokeren to the inhabitants regarding German occupation of the town.
- Leaflet, "Von allen Fronten. Neue italienische Offensive in Albanien,", undated (Box-folder 5: 17)
- Leaflet, "Wie würde es uns schädigen?,", undated (Box-folder 5: 18)
- Leaflets and flyers about purchasing Liberty Loans, 1917 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  Flyers are in English, French, Italian, Polish, and Russian. One leaflet is titled "Sermonic Suggestions, Second Liberty Loan Sunday, October 20-21, 1917." The other is titled "The Duty of the American Government to our Soldiers and Sailors--The Second Liberty Loan and the War Insurance Law," an address by Honorable W.G. McAdoo, Secretary of the Treasury, to the National Army at Camp Lewis, American Lake, Washington, October 9, 1917.
- Leaflets from the Joint Committee, Board of Agriculture and Ministry of Food, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  Leaflets 10a ("Small and Additional Acreage Order, 1918. Important to Small-Holders, Allotment-Holders, Farmers, Grist Millers and Others"), 10b ("Small and Additional Acreage Order, 1918. Important to Farmers, Grist Millers and Others in England and Wales"), and 10c ("Damaged Grain. Notice to Farmers").
- Leaflets about and by the German army, 1914-1917 (Box-folder 5: 21)
  In German. Includes typed annotations with brief commentary (in English).
- Map, Austria-Hungary, undated (Box-folder 5: 22)
- Map, Bartholomew's War Map of Asia Minor, Arabia, Persia, &c., undated (Box-folder 5: 23)
- Map, Boppard, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 24)
- Map, Königreich Böhmen/Royaume de Bohème, circa 1910 (Box-folder 5: 25)
- Map, The Large Scale Liberty War Map, Indexed, of the Western Front, with Inset of Central Europe, 1917 (Box-folder 5: 26)
- Map, Mayen, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 27)
- Map, St. Quentin, circa 1916 (Box-folder 5: 28)
- Map, Die Vereinigten Staaten von Gross-Österreich, undated (Box-folder 5: 29)
- Map, Western Front, Battle of the Somme, circa 1916 (Box-folder 5: 30)
- Map, The Western Theatre of the European War, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 31)
- Matrix for French propaganda print, undated (Box-folder 5: 32)
  Features engraving of a German soldier who appears to be tied up with pins stuck in him.
- Notebook, undated (Box-folder 5: 33)
  Appears to be in English. Handwritten.
- Print, "L'Alsace n'oublie pas…,", undated (Box-folder 5: 34)
  Black and white print shows women (possibly nuns) kneeling in black dresses and headdresses. Above them is text that reads "L'Alsace n'oublie pas que quinze cent mille soldats français sont morts pour sa delivrance."
- Programs and menus, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 5: 35)
  Includes some programs from Handforth Prisoner of War Camp in England (materials in German); a program from the Great American Matinee, 8 December 1916, in England; a program from Manifestation Nationale des Grandes Associations Françaises (materials in French); and a souvenir menu with (reproduced) signatures of the defenders of Verdun, featuring a photograph of Kathleen Burke of the Scottish Women's Hospitals (materials in English and French).
- Stamps, undated (Box-folder 5: 36)
  Includes stamps from special commemorative sets (e.g., "Timbres de l'Armée").
- Table, "Scales of Rations - Maximum Weekly Quantities,", 1918 June 1 (Box-folder 5: 37)
  Produced by the Public Services Branch Food Survey Board, Great Britain.
- Blueprints, Type de baraquement militaire démontable: systéme Adrian, 1915-1918 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  For military barracks.
- Clippings, George F. Rand and the Bayonet Trench Monument, 1919-1922, 1926, 1950 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  The first set of clippings, from roughly September 1919 to April 1920 (plus one post card from August 1922), concerns George F. Rand, and mainly consists of obituaries published after his untimely death in a plane crash. The second set of clippings, from roughly May 1920 to January 1921, concerns the building and dedication of the Bayonet Trench Monument, which Rand funded. There is also an article from January 1926 about the tragedy of the Bayonet Trench, as well as a letter from January 1950 to a relative of Rand's about the Monument at Verdun. It appears that some of the clippings, which were glued onto pages, are missing. Others were loose and did not appear to match any of the existing pages.
- Printed matter, relief organizations, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 6: 3)